<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?> 
<!-- $Header$ -->
<site:page
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	xmlns:site="http://www.lowagie.com/iText/site" >
	<site:metadata>
		<site:title>Download iText</site:title>
		<site:summary>How-to download iText (sourcecode and released jars)</site:summary>
		<site:keywords>PDF, JAVA, iText, download, release, Lowagie, Bruno</site:keywords>
		<site:amazonbooks>
			<site:book asin="1932394796">iText in Action</site:book>
		</site:amazonbooks>
		<site:updated>$Date: 2008-04-18 16:50:32 -0400 (Fri, 18 Apr 2008) $</site:updated>
	</site:metadata>
	<site:content>
	<div>
	<div class="header">Download iText</div>
<div class="title">License Agreement</div>
iText is published under 2 different licenses: MPL and LGPL.<br /><br />
If you are a new user of iText, MPL is recommended (without the LGPL).
MPL is less strict than LGPL. Please read the
<a href="MPL-1.1.txt" class="normal">MPL license agreement</a>
before downloading and/or using iText.<br />
LGPL is maintained for backward compatibility only.
If you choose the LGPL, you need to mention the MPL as an alternative license.
Please read the <a href="lgpl.txt" class="normal">LGPL license agreement</a>
for more info.<br /><br />
This library is free and I want it to stay free: you can use it without paying
a fee; you don't need to register anywhere. Only keep in mind that agreeing
with the license is crucial to protect the software, its developers and its users.
This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT
any warranty. If you don't like free software, don't (ab)use it!
<div class="title">Current release</div>
The release on this site is <site:releasenumber />.<br /><br />
<table align="center" border="1" cellpadding="3" cellspacing="0" width="80%">
	<tr><th colspan="2">Download the library:</th></tr>
	<tr>
		<td width="20%" class="small">Source code</td>
		<td class="small"><site:releasesrc /></td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td width="20%" class="small">Compiled code</td>
		<td class="small"><site:releasejar /></td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td width="20%" class="small">Documentation</td>
		<td class="small"><site:releasedocs /></td>
	</tr>
</table><br />
Please consult the <a href="http://www.1t3xt.com/about/history.php">history overview</a> for more info.<br />
Another option to get the source code is to download it from the <a href="svn.html">SVN repository</a>.
There, you'll always find the most recent iText version, and even some branches to build your
own jar for the older JDK 1.3 or newer JDKs such as JDK 1.5.
<div class="title">Getting older versions of iText</div>
Older versions of iText are archived at SourceForge; see the <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=15255&amp;package_id=12596">release list @ SourceForge</a>.
Please understand that we can't give support for versions that are more than one year old. However, you can always download those old versions and try to apply bugfixes that were
added to later releases to the version of iText you need in your applications.
	</div>
	</site:content>
</site:page>