<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?> 
<!-- $Header$ -->
<site:page
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	xmlns:site="http://www.lowagie.com/iText/site" >
	<site:metadata>
		<site:title>Privacy Policy</site:title>
		<site:summary>My policy if you visit my site or join the mailing-list</site:summary>
		<site:keywords>PDF, JAVA, iText, privacy policy, Lowagie, Bruno</site:keywords>
		<site:amazonbooks>
			<site:book asin="0817998926">Public Policy and the Internet</site:book>
			<site:book asin="0321304748">PDF Reference (4th Edition)</site:book>
		</site:amazonbooks>
		<site:updated>$Date: 2008-04-18 16:50:32 -0400 (Fri, 18 Apr 2008) $</site:updated>
	</site:metadata>
	<site:content>
	<div>
<div class="header">Privacy Policy</div>
<div class="title">Concerning the Web Site:</div>
IP addresses of visitors to the lowagie.com site are used to help diagnose problems
with the server and to administer the Web site. IP addresses are also used to compile
general demographic information (see for instance http://www.lowagie.com/logs/).
There will be no attempts to identify individual users through their IP addresses,
unless the user had malicious intents when visiting the site (for instance if the
user tried to crack the website).<br />
<br />
Sometimes an outside ad company is allowed to display ads on our site. These ads may
contain cookies. Cookies received with banner ads may be collected by the ad company,
and we do not have access to this information. The site lowagie.com itself does not
currently use cookies, but it may use (non-persistent) cookies in the future.
Cookies may be used to make sure you don't see the same ad repeatedly as well as to
deliver content specific to your interests.
<div class="title">Concerning Mailing list(s):</div>
If you subscribe to any mailing list featured on lowagie.com, your email address
will be used only to send you the mails posted to this list and not for any other
purpose. Email addresses of mailing list subscribers are never given or sold to
third parties. You can unsubscribe from the mailing list(s) at any time, just by
following the instructions sent to you when you subscribed.<br />
<br />
If your mail contains a bugreport, bugfix or code contribution, your name and
(in some cases) your email-address (but you can refuse this) will be added into
the source code, tutorial, history-file,...
<div class="title">Concerning External Links:</div>
This site contains links to other sites. The people behind lowagie.com are not
responsible for the privacy practices or the content of such Web sites.
<div class="title">Contacting the Web Site:</div>
If you have any questions about this privacy statement, the practices of this site,
or your dealings with this Web site, you can contact: bruno@lowagie.com
	</div>
	</site:content>
</site:page>