<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?> 
<!-- $Header: /cvsroot/itext/www/lowagie/cvs.xml,v 1.2 2006/05/22 11:00:29 blowagie Exp $ -->
<site:page
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	xmlns:site="http://www.lowagie.com/iText/site" >
	<site:metadata>
		<site:title>Install development environment</site:title>
		<site:summary>How I install my development environment for iText.</site:summary>
		<site:keywords>PDF, JAVA, iText, download, source, development environment</site:keywords>
		<site:amazonbooks>
			<site:book asin="1932394796">iText in Action</site:book>
		</site:amazonbooks>
		<site:updated>$Date: 2008-04-18 16:50:32 -0400 (Fri, 18 Apr 2008) $</site:updated>
	</site:metadata>
	<site:content>
	<div>
<div class="header">How I install my development environment for iText (SVN)</div>
Every time I upgrade my hardware (for instance when I buy a new portable),
I have to set up my development environment from scratch. Because I don't
buy a new computer every month, I often forget which steps are necessary.
That's why I wrote these pages: it's a checklist for myself, that can be useful
for others too. That is: if you want to download iText from SVN and build the
iText.jar yourself.
<a name="requirements"> </a>
<div class="title">Requirements</div>
First let's have a look at the tools or products that are on another (not iText-related) checklest.
It's the stuff I install without thinking; you may already have most of it on your computer:
<ul>
<li>An operation system: iText is a Java library, so it doesn't
really matter which operating system you use. I use iText on Windows
and the GNU Operation System with a Linux kernel (wink at Richard S.)
depending on what I intend to do with the new computer (development and
demos: Windows; server and production: Linux).<br />
Let me explain how I set up my environment on Windows, as people
using Linux are supposed to know what they are doing.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.eclipse.org/">Eclipse:</a> Paulo uses <a href="http://www.netbeans.org/">NetBeans</a>;
I have used NetBeans in the past (when it was still called Forte4Java),
I have used IntelliJ, I even started my carreer in Java using Visual J++ Studio
(because it was shipped on a CD that accompanied my first book on Java).
Tired of switching from one IDE to another, I decided to use Eclipse,
and now I stick with it. My advise is: work on iText with the IDE you think is
the most comfortable for you! For me, it's Eclipse; for you it might be
NetBeans. It doesn't really matter.</li>
<li><a href="http://tortoisesvn.net/">TortoiseSVN:</a> the most recent iText code base
is stored in a <a href="http://itext.svn.sourceforge.net/viewvc/itext/trunk/">Subversion repository at SourceForge</a>.
I use Tortoise SVN to access this repository.</li>
<li><a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4.2/download.html">Java version 1.4.2:</a> for now, the official releases of iText use
the JDK 1.4. We don't use newer JDKs, out of respect for the many users that
aren't ready to make the change to Java 5 or Java 6 yet. People that are
still using JDK 1.3: please create your own jar.</li>
</ul>
Did you manage installing all this on your computer?
Then let's move on to the iText related stuff.
<a name="checkout"> </a>
<div class="title">Getting iText from SVN</div>
First I make a directory <code>C:/itext-core</code>.
I also have directories <code>C:/itext-toolbox</code>,
<code>C:/itext-book</code>, <code>C:/itext-articles</code>,
and so on, but that doesn't matter right now, we only
want to install the development environment for iText.<br />
In this itext-core directory, I usually create a subdirectory
<code>C:/itext-core/main</code>:
<div class="figure"><img src="images/directory.png" /></div>
<br />
This isn't really necessary, but I use this so that I can use
the itext-core directory as an Eclipse Workspace, and main as
one of the projects in this workspace. Another project I always
create is test in directory c:/itext-core/test, but let's not
get ahead of ourselves.<br />
Next we rightclick and select <code>SVN Checkout...:</code><br />
<div class="figure"><img src="images/tortoise.png" /></div>
<br />
This opens the following dialogbox:<br />
<div class="figure"><img src="images/checkout.png" /></div>
<br />
The string you need is:
<div class="commandline">https://itext.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/itext/trunk</div>
This will download everything you need to download the current version
of iText. You can browse this version online at this address:
<a href="http://itext.svn.sourceforge.net/viewvc/itext/trunk/">http://itext.svn.sourceforge.net/viewvc/itext/trunk/</a><br />
If you need a branch or an old version that was tagged, you'll have
to adapt the URL of the SVN repository. Browse the following URL for
inspiration: <a href="http://itext.svn.sourceforge.net/viewvc/itext/">http://itext.svn.sourceforge.net/viewvc/itext/</a><br />
While you browse these URLs, tortoiseSVN is downloading the trunk like this:<br />
<div class="figure"><img src="images/source.png" /></div>
<br />
Once this process is finished, you end up with these subdirectories:<br />
<div class="figure"><img src="images/checked_out.png" /></div>
<br />
This is an overview of the directories that were created:
<ul>
<li><b>.svn:</b> Please ignore this directory, it contains information that
is used by Subversion (for instance to check if the code was changed).</li>
<li><b>lib:</b> a typical lib directory containing some jars that are
needed to compile iText (more specifically the bcmail and bcprov jars
from BouncyCastle) and some jars that are needed to compile and run the
iText examples.</li>
<li><b>src:</b> the source code and everything you need to create your
own iText.jar.</li>
<li><b>www:</b> everything <i>I</i> need to create some of the iText sites;
including the tutorial examples.</li>
</ul>
You can now <a href="eclipse.html">create a workspace in Eclipse</a>.
	</div>
	</site:content>
</site:page>