<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?> 
<site:page
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	xmlns:site="http://www.lowagie.com/iText/site" >
	<site:metadata>
		<site:title status="finished">RTF generation settings</site:title>
		<site:summary>How to configure settings for the RTF generation.</site:summary>
		<site:keywords>JAVA, iText, RTF, examples</site:keywords>
		<site:amazonbooks>
			<site:book asin="0596004753">RTF Pocket Guide</site:book>
			<site:keyword>JAVA</site:keyword>
			<site:keyword>RTF</site:keyword>
		</site:amazonbooks>
		<site:updated>$Date: 2008-05-16 12:35:34 -0400 (Fri, 16 May 2008) $</site:updated>
		<site:author>Mark Hall</site:author>
	</site:metadata>
	
	<site:examples>
		<site:example>
			<site:java src="DocumentSettings" standalone="yes" />
			<site:result>DocumentSettings.rtf</site:result>
			<site:extrajar>itext-rtf.jar</site:extrajar>
			<site:description>Generates a simple document with modified document settings</site:description>
		</site:example>
	</site:examples>

	<site:chapter>
    <site:section name="settings">
    	<site:sectiontitle>RTF generation settings</site:sectiontitle>
    	<div>
    	  The RtfWriter2 supports a set of configuration switches that can be used to
    	  tailor the RTF generated.
    	  <dl>
    	    <dt style="font-weight: bold;">outputTableRowDefinitionAfter (Boolean)</dt>
    	    <dd>Whether to write the table row definitions both before and after
    	      the table data. Set to <span class="commandline">true</span> if you
    	      are generating RTF documents that need to be read with Word 2000.
    	      Set to <span class="commandline">false</span> if you are generating
    	      RTF documents that need to be read with OpenOffice.org Writer. By
    	      default table row definitions are written both before and after.</dd>
    	    <dt style="font-weight: bold;">alwaysGenerateSoftLinebreaks (Boolean)</dt>
    	    <dd>Whether \n characters should be written as hard or soft linebreaks.
    	      By default only \n characters in lists and table cells are written as
    	      soft linebreaks. Setting this property to <span class="commandline">true</span>
    	      causes all \n characters to be written as soft linebreaks.s</dd>
    	    <dt style="font-weight: bold;">alwaysUseUnicode (Boolean)</dt>
    	    <dd>Whether all characters bigger than 'z' should be written as unicode escapes
    	      or whether the original character should be written. The default is to escape
    	      everything, which leads to larger RTF files. Setting this property to 
    	      <span class="commandline">false</span> reduces RTF file size, but may lead
    	      to characters being displayed incorrectly.</dd>
    	    <dt style="font-weight: bold;">dataCacheStyle (Integer)</dt>
    	    <dd>Specifies where the RTF document is cached during document generation. Valid
    	      values are specified in the <site:doc class="com.lowagie.text.rtf.document.output.RtfDataCache">RtfDataCache</site:doc>.
    	      <ul>
    	        <li>CACHE_MEMORY: The default keeps the whole document in memory. This increases
    	          the generation speed, but places a maximum size on the document.</li>
    	        <li>CACHE_MEMORY_EFFICIENT: The document is kept in memory, but the use of memory
    	          is minimised. Depending on how your document is structured, using this might
    	          slightly slow down the generation speed, but should reduce the memory footprint
    	          by at least 50%.</li>
    	        <li>Cache_DISK: The document is cached on disk. This decreases the document generation
    	          speed, but the maximum document size is increased to the amount of space free
    	          on the disk.</li>
    	      </ul>
    	      You can only set this property before calling <span class="commandline">document.open()</span>.
    	    </dd>
    	    <dt style="font-weight: bold;">outputDebugLineBreaks (Boolean)</dt>
    	    <dd>This setting is primarily for debugging purposes and leads to slightly larger,
    	      but more readable RTF files. Set it to <span class="commandline">false</span>
    	      to decrease the RTF file size.</dd>
    	    <dt style="font-weight: bold;">imagePDFConformance (Boolean)</dt>
    	    <dd>This setting controls whether images are scaled so that the result is equivalent to
    	      the PDF display. Defaults to <span class="commandline">true</span>. The result of this
    	      is that images are added at 72 DPI and if any other resolution is required, this must
    	      be achieved through scaling. Set it to <span class="commandline">false</span> to 
    	      add images with the default RTF resolution.</dd>
    	    <dt style="font-weight: bold;">writeImageScalingInformation (Boolean)</dt>
    	    <dd>Whether to write additional styling information that is required to display scaled
    	      images correctly in Word 2000, Word 97 and Word for Mac. Defaults to
    	      <span class="commandline">false</span>. If you want images to be scaled correctly
    	      in Word 2000, Word 97 and Word for Mac set this setting to <span class="commandline">true</span>.
    	      Must be <span class="commandline">false</span> for images to be displayed correctly
    	      in Word XP.</dd>
            <dt style="font-weight: bold;">imageWrittenAsBinary (Boolean)</dt>
            <dd>This setting controls whether images are written as binary data in the RTF document, or are
              hex encoded. Defaults to <span class="commandline">true</span> for document size reasons. Set to
              <span class="commandline">false</span> if you want hex encoded image data.</dd>
    	  </dl>
    	  You access these generation settings by getting the <span class="commandline">RtfDocumentSettings</span>
    	  object from the <span class="commandline">RtfWriter2</span>.
    	  <pre class="commandline">
Document document = new Document();
RtfWriter2 writer2 = RtfWriter2.getInstance(document,
	new FileOutputStream("rtfDocumentSettings.rtf"));

// Access the RtfDocumentSettings and set the desired properties	
writer2.getRtfDocumentSettings().setDataCacheStyle(RtfDataCache.CACHE_DISK);

document.open();
...
document.close();
    	  </pre>
          <site:source class="DocumentSettings" />
    	</div>
    </site:section>
    
    <site:section name="shortcuts">
    	<site:sectiontitle>Viewer version settings</site:sectiontitle>
    	<div>
    	  The <site:doc class="com.lowagie.text.rtf.document.RtfDocumentSettings">RtfDocumentSettings</site:doc> also provides a number of
    	  methods to set generation options for specific viewers. These act as shortcuts to
    	  set a number of the generation settings listed above. Methods for the following viewers
    	  are provided
    	  <ul>
    	    <li><b>Word 2000 and 97</b>: Sets the options for Word 2000 and Word 97 compliance -
    	      <span class="commandline">outputTableRowDefinitionAfter = true</span> and
    	      <span class="commandline">writeImageScalingInformation = true</span></li>
    	    <li><b>Word for Mac</b>: Sets the options for Word for Mac compliance - 
    	      <span class="commandline">writeImageScalingInformation = true</span></li>
    	    <li><b>Word XP</b>: Sets the options for Word XP compliance - 
    	      <span class="commandline">writeImageScalingInformation = false</span></li>
    	    <li><b>OpenOffice.org</b>: Sets the options for OpenOffice.org compliance - 
    	      <span class="commandline">outputTableRowDefinitionAfter = true</span></li>
    	  </ul><br />
    	  
    	  You should only call one of these methods as they are partially mutually exclusive.
    	</div>
    </site:section>
    </site:chapter>
    
</site:page>