<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?> 
<site:page
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	xmlns:site="http://www.lowagie.com/iText/site" >
	<site:metadata>
		<site:title status="finished">PdfPTable</site:title>
		<site:summary>Some extra PdfPTable functionality</site:summary>
		<site:keywords>PDF, JAVA, iText, PdfPTable, Table, Lowagie, Bruno</site:keywords>
		<site:amazonbooks>
			<site:book asin="1932394796">iText in Action</site:book>
			<site:book asin="0321304748">PDF Reference (4th Edition)</site:book>
			<site:keyword>JAVA</site:keyword>
		</site:amazonbooks>
		<site:updated>$Date: 2008-04-18 16:50:32 -0400 (Fri, 18 Apr 2008) $</site:updated>
		<site:author>Bruno Lowagie</site:author>
	</site:metadata>
	
	<site:examples>
		<site:example>
			<site:java src="WriteSelectedRows" standalone="yes" />
			<site:result>WriteSelectedRows.pdf</site:result>
			<site:description>Demonstrates the writeSelectedRows method</site:description>
		</site:example>
		<site:example>
			<site:java src="Tables" standalone="yes" />
			<site:result>tables.pdf</site:result>
			<site:description>Adds a table to an absolute position</site:description>
		</site:example>
		<site:example>
			<site:java src="SplitTable" standalone="yes" />
			<site:result>SplitTable.pdf</site:result>
			<site:description>Demonstrates how to split a Table in two sections of columns</site:description>
		</site:example>
		<site:example>
			<site:java src="FragmentTable" standalone="yes" />
			<site:result>FragmentTable.pdf</site:result>
			<site:argument>50</site:argument>
			<site:description>Break one large Table up into different smaller tables with the same header</site:description>
		</site:example>
		<site:example>
			<site:java src="CellEvents" standalone="yes" />
			<site:result>CellEvents.pdf</site:result>
			<site:externalresource>otsoe.jpg</site:externalresource>
			<site:description>Demonstrates what one can do with cell events</site:description>
		</site:example>
		<site:example>
			<site:java src="TableEvents1" standalone="yes" />
			<site:result>TableEvents1.pdf</site:result>
			<site:description>Demonstrates what one can do with table events</site:description>
		</site:example>
		<site:example>
			<site:java src="TableEvents2" standalone="yes" />
			<site:result>TableEvents2.pdf</site:result>
			<site:description>Demonstrates what one can do with table events (cells with colspan &gt; 1)</site:description>
		</site:example>
		<site:example>
			<site:java src="FloatingBoxes" standalone="yes" />
			<site:result>FloatingBoxes.pdf</site:result>
			<site:description>Demonstrates how to simulate cellspacing as in HTML</site:description>
		</site:example>
		<site:example>
			<site:java src="VerticalTextInCells" standalone="yes" />
			<site:result>VerticalText.pdf</site:result>
			<site:description>Demonstrates how to add vertical text in a cell</site:description>
		</site:example>
	</site:examples>
	
	<site:chapter>

	<site:section name="inaction">
		<site:sectiontitle>In the book</site:sectiontitle>
		<div>
		<site:book>
			<site:bookchapter chapter="6" />
		</site:book>
		</div>
	</site:section>
	<site:section new="writeselectedrows">
		<site:sectiontitle>Adding a PdfPTable at an absolute position</site:sectiontitle>
<div>
You can add a PdfPTable with <site:doc class="com.lowagie.text.Document" target="add(com.lowagie.text.Element)">Document.add()</site:doc>
as described in the <site:tutorial chapter="/objects/tables">previous chapter</site:tutorial>,
but you can also choose to put a PdfPTable at an absolute position with the method
<site:doc class="com.lowagie.text.pdf.PdfPTable" target="writeSelectedRows(int,%20int,%20float,%20float,%20com.lowagie.text.pdf.PdfContentByte)">writeSelectedRows</site:doc>.
The mechanisms to add objects at absolute positions will be described in
<site:tutorial chapter="" section="part4">Part IV</site:tutorial> of the tutorial.
All you need to know for now is that you have to pass the following parameters to the method:
<ul>
	<li>rowStart - the first row to be written, zero index</li>
	<li>rowEnd - the last row to be written + 1. If it is -1 all the rows to the end are written.</li>
	<li>xPos - the x write coodinate of the upper left corner of the table</li>
	<li>yPos - the y write coodinate of the upper left corner of the table (remark: the 0 is at the bottom of the page as explained in the <site:tutorial chapter="/general/faq" section="xycoordinates">FAQ</site:tutorial>)</li>
	<li>canvas - the PdfContentByte where the rows will be written to (explained in <site:tutorial chapter="" section="part4">Part IV</site:tutorial> of the tutorial)</li>
</ul>
<site:source class="WriteSelectedRows" />
<site:source class="Tables" />
As you can see in the example, there are some things you need to keep in mind
when using <site:doc class="com.lowagie.text.pdf.PdfPTable" target="writeSelectedRows(int,%20int,%20float,%20float,%20com.lowagie.text.pdf.PdfContentByte)">writeSelectedRows</site:doc>.
If you add a PdfPTable with document.add(), the width of the table
is always calculated as a percentage of the available page width at the current pointer
(see page 2 of the PDF in the example). But if you add a PdfPTable at
an absolute position, iText can't know what you are up to with the rest
of the page. What is the available space?
That's something iText can't know, so you need to set a total width of the Table with the methods
<site:doc class="com.lowagie.text.pdf.PdfPTable" target="setTotalWidth(float)">setTotalWidth(float totalWidth)</site:doc>
or <site:doc class="com.lowagie.text.pdf.PdfPTable" target="setTotalWidth(float[])">setTotalWidth(float[] columnWidth)</site:doc>.<br />
You are also responsible for checking it the PdfPTable fits on the page.
On page 5, rows 100-150 don't fit on the page because we started writing the rows at y = 200 instead of y = 820.
Rows 112-149 are written, but you can't see them because they are outside the visible area of your page.<br />
As you can see in the example, you can use
<site:doc class="com.lowagie.text.pdf.PdfPTable" target="writeSelectedRows(int,%20int,%20float,%20float,%20com.lowagie.text.pdf.PdfContentByte)">writeSelectedRows(int rowStart, int rowEnd, float xPos, float yPos, PdfContentByte canvas)</site:doc>
to split your table horizontally over different pages if you have too many rows to fit on one page.
If your table is too wide, you can also split the table vertically between columns.
You need the method
<site:doc class="com.lowagie.text.pdf.PdfPTable" target="writeSelectedRows(int,%20int,%20int,%20int,%20float,%20float,%20com.lowagie.text.pdf.PdfContentByte)">writeSelectedRows(int colStart, int colEnd, int rowStart, int rowEnd, float xPos, float yPos, PdfContentByte canvas)</site:doc>
to do this.
<site:source class="SplitTable" />
</div>
	</site:section>
	
	<site:section name="memory">
		<site:sectiontitle>Memory management for large tables</site:sectiontitle>
<div>
You have to be very careful with large tables.
When you add objects to a Document, these objects are written
to the outputstream 'as soon as possible'. The objects that have
been written are made eligible for destruction. However, when
you construct a PdfPTable and keep adding new cells without adding
the table to the document, the PdfPTable-object keeps on growing,
taking more and more memory that isn't being released.
For really large tables, this can become a serious problem.<br />
The next example shows how to split a table into different sections.
As the tables are glued to eachother (don't use <site:doc class="com.lowagie.text.pdf.PdfPTable" target="setSpacingBefore(float)">setSpacingBefore</site:doc>
and 
<site:doc class="com.lowagie.text.pdf.PdfPTable" target="setSpacingAfter(float)">setSpacingAfter</site:doc> here),
nobody will see the difference between 1 large table or several small tables.
<site:source class="FragmentTable" />
</div>
	</site:section>
	
	<site:section name="cellevents">
		<site:sectiontitle>Cell and Table Events</site:sectiontitle>
<div>
Remember the class <site:tutorial chapter="/objects/chunk" section="generic">Chunk</site:tutorial>
and how you could add your own functionality in a generic way with a PageEvent?
You can do the same with a PdfPCell using a <site:doc class="com.lowagie.text.pdf.PdfPCellEvent">PdfPCellEvent</site:doc>.
In the example, we want to strike a line OVER the contents from the lowerleft to the upperright corner.
Using methods that are explained in <site:tutorial chapter="" section="part4">Part IV</site:tutorial> of the tutorial, we can apply almost every layout that is possible within the PDF syntax.
We just have to implement the method
<site:doc class="com.lowagie.text.pdf.PdfPCellEvent" target="cellLayout(com.lowagie.text.pdf.PdfPCell,%20com.lowagie.text.Rectangle,%20com.lowagie.text.pdf.PdfContentByte[])">cellLayout</site:doc>.
You can use the cell itself that is passed as a parameter and you get a Rectangle object that holds to absolute position of the cell on the page.
The array of PdfContentByte arrays needs some further explanation:
<ul>
<li><site:doc class="com.lowagie.text.pdf.PdfPTable" target="BASECANVAS">PdfPtable.BASECANVAS</site:doc> - the original PdfContentByte. Anything placed here will be under the table.</li>
<li><site:doc class="com.lowagie.text.pdf.PdfPTable" target="BACKGROUNDCANVAS">PdfPtable.BACKGROUNDCANVAS</site:doc> - the layer where the background goes to.</li>
<li><site:doc class="com.lowagie.text.pdf.PdfPTable" target="LINECANVAS">PdfPtable.LINECANVAS</site:doc> - the layer where the lines go to.</li>
<li><site:doc class="com.lowagie.text.pdf.PdfPTable" target="TEXTCANVAS">PdfPtable.TEXTCANVAS</site:doc> - the layer where the text go to. Anything placed here will be over the table.</li>
</ul>
<site:source class="CellEvents" />
If you want the same kind of control over a complete table, it gets a little bit more complicated.
You need to implement the method <site:doc class="com.lowagie.text.pdf.PdfPTableEvent" target="tableLayout(com.lowagie.text.pdf.PdfPTable,%20float[][],%20float[],%20int,%20int,%20com.lowagie.text.pdf.PdfContentByte[])">tableLayout</site:doc> of
the <site:doc class="com.lowagie.text.pdf.PdfPTableEvent">PdfPTableEvent</site:doc> interface.
<site:source class="TableEvents1" />
<site:source class="TableEvents2" />
In the next example cell and table events are combined to simulate cellspacing.
<site:source class="FloatingBoxes" />
</div>
	</site:section>
	
	<site:section name="verticaltext">
		<site:sectiontitle>Vertical Text</site:sectiontitle>
<div>
Finally the answer to a question that pops up on the mailinglist from time to time:
is it possible to put vertical text in a Cell. The answer is: yes, but you need to know
how to use the class <site:doc class="com.lowagie.text.pdf.PdfTemplate">PdfTemplate</site:doc>
(which is explained in the <site:tutorial chapter="/directcontent" section="templates">direct content</site:tutorial> of the tutorial).
If you can't wait, just take a look at the following example.
<site:source class="VerticalTextInCells" />
</div>
	</site:section>
	</site:chapter>
</site:page>